[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software so I'm sitting here
with aghanim's Tarkin he has a PhD in
surf engineering and he is doing
architecture and consulting since more
than twenty years now
he co-founded I as a QB and that's the
international sofa he takes a
qualification board and has written
quite a few books about so far tech
chure mostly in German
hello about this is cannot thank you for
this introduction the the books I wrote
our many concerns with software
architecture and the probably most known
as the effective a software architect
one that translates to effective
software architectures covering mostly
everything that's currently important
and interesting about the topic I've
done some parent stuff some stuff on the
behavior of software architects how
architects shall deal with typical
problems and organizations and so on
yeah so thanks a lot for being on the
show you're working as a fellow for in
new countries like me and today's topic
is going to be about arc 42 that's in a
set of templates for documenting Safari
texture and it is something that you co
invented so first of all how did you
come up with this name arc 42 but maybe
I rephrase that question how did we come
up with that thing or the idea and the
history behind it is that Peter RushCard
the other guy and and me we sat together
and looked over a set of architectures
real software architectures we both have
built over the years and we discussed
the topics that we had included in these
architectures so we had a look at their
documentation at the code at the issues
we had been and that's the business and
stories of that and we found that in
many architectures we are talking about
the same things actually about the same
ideas and the same kind of questions
came up so we decided we could
derive some common structure from from
that and make this kind of architectural
template that was the birth of it and in
the beginning it had no name and then we
started using it in customer projects
and the customers wanted to know what
cool thing that is and I'm talking about
a thing that has no name is possible in
Harry Potter stories but it's it's
really difficult in IT industry so we
were forced to invent a name and
actually the cool domains the great
software architecture template con was
not free so we had to find something
with a with an available domain and
architecture a Arceus was not free but
architecture 42 was so we we decided
that because this domain was free and I
think every everybody knows what 42 is
all about yeah I guess that's true
that's great quite interesting and I
like how it's actually derived from
practical work so who's behind the
project right now as it is from the
start that's more than 10 years ago we
decided it should be an open thing and
in the first couple of years the only
contributors to this open source thing
were beta and myself but over the time a
few customers joined us and left like
its usual in open source but the main
forces is currently about 3/4 committers
we can find out sandy and the open
github project but beta booshka and
myself are the let's say major forces
and a few others contribute to the
technology in generating the stuff and
and some some tooling support
excellently so you said it it's free so
how is it license a couple of years ago
we decided we should have any license
and and we decided that the Creative
Commons license would be good so we
encourage customers to use it as it is
and if they like they they should quote
us if they change the structure of the
template they don't even need to quote
so it's absolutely free and people are
using it in quite restricted domains and
using it for open-source project so it's
definitely free to use as you like it so
the license is a Creative Commons or
some kind of yes we call it a Creative
Commons license it we like to be quoted
if so if you
use it without any any modification so
if you invest your own time to change
the structure and to add things then you
don't even need to quote us ok I see and
who's using it I have to admit that I
don't know that I get feedback from all
over the at least Central European
industries I've seen it in German
Austria Switzerland and many smaller and
larger enterprises like banks telecom
logistics and so on
I've seen it in the the eastern
countries I know from some companies in
China and Russia using it and we get we
get questions from American companies
since it's quite an old idea it has been
on the market for several years I think
the the usage is quite broad to me it
seems that it's sort of the default that
you use in at least in Germany I thank
you and that was actually one of the
reasons to do this show because it seems
to be such a huge thing in Germany and I
thought it might be interesting to to
also see what what foreign people think
about it and and get some information
out about it so if you talk about
architecture and how to document
architecture there is obviously UML so
what's the relation between our 42 and
UML one step back the the relation
between act 42 and UML is none
whatsoever
so you can use one or the other for
their purposes but you don't need to use
any UML to document an architecture and
you can draw images on a whiteboard or
on your hotel wall if you like and you
could use ml to describe several aspects
of of technical systems but there is no
need to do so I personally do use UML
because it's a quite strictly defined
language and there is really nice tools
for it but I have lots of customer
situations without an UML tool and I can
successfully document architectures ok I
see I mean if you if you talk about
Isaac Trent how you do I detect Rand
documentation and so on is it something
that you do upfront or is it a draw I
mean the Etra guys say that you don't
need any big design up front least
something that are for two supports to
not do it all at once at the start of
the project we make no assumption and I
underline that no assumption at all
about your process so I know that arc 42
is used in heavy design industries like
safety critical systems but it's also
used in very agile projects it's
completely independent of the process
because it's it's a tool to communicate
ideas and decisions if you take your
decisions in a very agile way you can
document your decisions in a very agile
way and it's like two different
questions to ask how do I design my
system if I do that upfront or agile and
how do I communicate my ideas and that's
a completely independent decision how
you communicate I am I am since years a
big big friend of Adrian tough of a lot
of iteration and feedback things and
that fits quite well together with AK 42
are there any other projects that you're
aware of or is it something that that
only you guys are doing this kind of
architecture documentation template
thing especially in larger organizations
I have seen loads of different design
and architectural templates some of them
are missing stuff some of them are even
more comprehensive than arc 42 but most
of those our company internal only Simon
Brown with the software architects
architecture for developers has derived
a similar thing from the content and
some basic ideas we are quite closely
together although the names differ but I
am not aware of any open or completely
free alternatives to AK 42 there have
been some initiatives by HP and by IBM
and by some universities with
architectural description languages but
these are not as comprehensive or are
and not as neutral domain neutral as our
act 42 is so Simon's Park is also not
sourced and Simon's work is open but he
uses some some just a different naming
than then we do and I have actually not
seen his work in clients I work with
I know Simon from from conferences and
know his books is a great experience and
it was great fun comparing his his kind
of documentation to ours and we found
many similarities commonalities and that
would be a real alternative so if I
needed to do documentation and had no
chance to use my own template I would
use his okay that's great so one thing
that I was wondering is should
documentation be executable I believe
that if a diagram becomes code or if a
requirement actually becomes an
executable test that's generally a good
idea because it means that the
requirements is actually really
fulfilled by the by the software and
it's provable so I was wondering whether
there is any similar thing for the
documentation to make sure that
documentation and code matches and that
everything is working together nicely
yeah that's an awesome idea too bad I
encounter it only rarely in the industry
in real practice I would like to do that
and we had we have some great examples
like 42 examples where we have parts of
the documentation being taken from the
from github repositories or git
repositories and directly included after
testing in the documentation so that's
it's possible it obviously depends on
your tool chain so it doesn't depend on
our 42 as a as a templating concept but
on tools and the same is valid for a UML
and generating code from your L models
that's a great idea to include such
models in your documentation describe
your tool chain with it and your you're
done that's that would be a great idea
so if I could decide freely decide how
to document I would try to incorporate
important source code artifacts that are
tested and really current from the from
the repositories in the architectural
documentation but have you ever seen
that in our
and any of your clients probably put
that in the show notes we have an open
example of is a quite small open source
projects where we have that that's a
direct inclusion of source code in the
documentation as I said and in customer
projects it's quite rare because it
takes some effort to get the two chains
up and running and and the customers
want a safe budget and say this is a
long-term investment we do it next year
and then it gets dumped and over and
over again and the other way around that
is stuff from the documentation is taken
and somehow executed or made part of the
code just that ever I have not seen that
in reality I know that some fancy book
authors write their books so the code
examples from the books get executed and
we try to incorporate some of these
ideas in act 42 but this this is valid
in real innovative projects but it
didn't work out in larger enterprises so
far yeah I have to admit that with my
books I'm also lazy so I don't do that
he does okay so we've spoken a lot about
what on high-level what it is and what
you're aiming for so we thought that we
would give a short overview about arc 42
itself and we would encourage you to
take a look at all the diagrams by
yourself and so we are definitely going
to include some links in the show notes
and it does make a lot of sense to
describe every diagram in detail
obviously because it's it's visual by
nature but we should at least talk about
the parts and how they fit together
yeah about may I correct a few of your
statements you are talking about
diagrams and not all documentation
consists of diagrams I know that you
write textual documentation to explain
your decisions and so on so and please
let our listeners and not only focus on
images and pictures but there has to be
some textural or tabular explanation to
a picture and many parts of our 42 are
relying on textual arguments on
describing a decision that can be done
without any visuals it can be done quite
low-tech and without drawing anything
just describing your idea and
yeah that's that's a very good point so
high tech chure is definitely not just
about drawing diagrams let's talk about
the parts of arc 42 then so the first
part that you said is to define what the
problem actually is so why do I need
that part
I mean is it obvious what I'm supposed
to do it might be obvious in a few
people's head but we are writing
documentation for probably some today
unknown stakeholders unknown readers for
the future and they probably have a
different idea of what the product is
supposed to do so I think it's a good
idea it's a good practice to describe
what's the fundamental business goal of
any product to enable readers or
consumers of documentation to understand
design decisions better I I like to
describe a bit of the functional parts
of the problem and I like to describe
part of the of the constraints I'm
developing under so for example if
people tell me you are not allowed any
functional language or a you are not
allowed any fancy in no sequel database
and I need that information to
understand decisions I take on later
that's quite interesting my impression
is when I look at some projects that
actually the architects don't really
know what the problem is and in some
cases they just jump to conclusions and
start to to come up with some kind of AI
structure without really understanding
the the trade-offs that they would need
to do and I think that's actually quite
a bad thing because if you don't know
what the problem is you can't come up
with a good solution so what do you
think about that is it just me that sees
these kinds of problems you you have
just described the reason why we put
this part into our 42 to really ensure
that there is a common knowledge about
the problem domain we don't want to copy
the rienne any requirements
documentation here just as much to give
an architect or other developers an
overview what are the requirements what
are the required quality goals how
secure
flexible anything should be to really
ensure there is a common understanding
to make this understanding explicit and
I have experienced exactly the same
situation people designing solutions for
requirements that doesn't exist yeah
that's that's really bad that's waste of
money and time yeah so I have to to tell
this short story so I've seen a tweet
quite recently that said scalability is
actually a luxury problem because if you
have a scalability problem then it means
that you're already successful and I I
for one I see too many architects
carrying about scalability instead of
well getting stuff out quickly to prove
the business case for example yes and
having a scale yeah I I had similar
experiences with rather large clients
that try to design a scalable system and
the product wasn't successful and they
had an interesting solution but no
business and that's a bad thing so make
sure in our 42 with as few chapters or a
few compartments for information like
functional stuff and constraints and
context and so on that really constrain
and describe the problem domain okay as
far as I understood there is a part that
gives an introduction in goals so what
would you consist of for example the
major use cases or epics whatever you'd
like to call them the functional aspect
of the system give an overview who are
important stakeholders with their their
specific requirements and yeah describe
a bit about the quality goals actually
what are your top quality of top quality
priorities do you want to build highly
reliable system or a highly secure
system or a highly flexible system and
as in real world you cannot have
everything in perfection so you need to
make compromises and I want to know what
are my rules for for compromise yeah my
he section is all about trade-offs and I
want to know this is kind of trade-off
information quality goal information in
my introduction then there are
constraints so what would that be I have
a lot of clients that have
a predefined technology stack so some
people want to build java applications
others are more in the in the.net
Microsoft domain others say oh we got
this big mainframe and we want to
continue developing for the mainframe so
they constrain my technology decisions
and I think that constraint should be
part of the architecture documentation
to keep them for the future otherwise
you wouldn't understand what strange
decision I took if you don't know the
constraints I see and then there is the
context in project management
terminology I would describe this as the
scoping of the system so what's my
responsibility what do I have to build
and to what parts of the environment I
have to connect now in the context in
the architecture terminology I usually
describe my major external interfaces
like data sources or data sinks or event
sources or that kind of stuff they put
some of the the problem and and give an
idea about what problem the
architectures actually trying to solve
yeah so the next part would be about the
solution structure yeah that's
definitely the major part of the
architecture documentation describing
meza the most important artifact
describing your high level code
structure or subsystems you are a
component structure how your application
is built up from code there are some
solution ideas and strategies yeah
solution idea could be we we take this
of that kind of frameworks we reuse this
or that part of an existing application
we are using standard software for this
and that part of the problem and so on
so this very high-level introduction
into the kind of big solution ideas and
next thing I want to know is how is your
code structured so what's the top level
structure of your code what kind of
subsystems exist subsystem boundaries
exist so those will be the the building
blocks yes that would probably be
somewhere I would draw a diagram I guess
we we distinguish in at 42 between black
boxes and white boxes and for white
boxes you open up the structure and
therefore you need a diagram or I
propose you use diagrams for this
kind of information UML has a part in
that
I like component diagrams and package
diagrams for describing building block
views code structures but you could
photograph flip chart or whatever you
you need or you seem fit for such
structural information important thing
here is the mapping to the code so I
want and no fantasy diagrams but I want
to know how really the code fits
together in form of components or as we
call them building blocks yeah I think
that's another very important part that
the concept of the architecture must be
represented in the code basically
because otherwise it does make a lot of
sense yeah so and there is a runtime
view yeah because often from the code
it's difficult to understand how the
system really works so how things behave
over time what's done first and what
component is taking what
responsibilities after some other thing
happens so the order of events the order
of processing can be derived from
reading a lot of source code but I can
convey ideas on a very high level within
a few sketches or words or a numbered
list whatever to describe this has to
happen first and that thing has to
happen next and only third is probably
this and that sounds a little bit like
you would do it in in text not as a
diagram you could do both I like
sequence diagrams if I have a precise
overview of what's happening
I like numbered lists if I'm just
discussing ok so quite often if there is
a really important interaction in the
system will stick to numbered lists and
discussion for a long time and if we
want if we decide we want to keep this
information we probably transform it
into a diagram because sometimes
diagrams are easier to read and that
they are more difficult to write and
then there is a deployment view
obviously all our software has to run on
some hardware and the mapping from the
software to the hardware is quite often
a complex process in distributed systems
in even in simple client-server systems
you have several machines where you have
to deploy certain parts of your system
and these deployment rules are not
obvious
it's an active decision what building
blocks what components you bundle
together for one server and what others
you bundle together for another machine
therefore we have that deployment view
that contains physical information
hardware networks and so on to ensure
that this mapping from code to hardware
is understood okay makes no sense it
does it also work the other way around
so do you think that infrastructure also
has an impact on the architecture or is
it just that infrastructure is an
afterthought or in something that comes
out of the architecture I think this is
one of the major driving forces for an
architect and I need to make sure my
code is able to run on the
infrastructure so if I can decide the
infrastructure completely independent
and I could do it afterwards but usually
in my cases and major corporations we
have an infrastructure and we have
infrastructure constraints so I have to
make sure my software works on that
existing infrastructure okay in probably
in modern world very innovative
container based systems I have a lot of
freedom in that case but very often you
interface integrate with existing
systems even existing hardware and
infrastructure is a big driving force if
you violate that that idea your system
gets dumped what run yeah it's it's
probably the SATA state that you can be
in right it's going to be finished but
some time to go into production okay so
that's the solution structure with all
the different parts and and how it's how
it's going to work yeah let me add one
one fact here we describe this this
parts of AK 42 in this order from
problem to solution but in reality you
will work on these parts properly in a
completely different way in projects
I've seen we started with discussing
deployment options so we started
documenting the architecture and by the
deployment view so we had some
infrastructure sketches and then we
designed the firewalls around it the
firewall rules and in this architecture
and
only after that we started discussing
use cases and and so on so the order in
which you work might be completely
independent of the order we use this in
our 42 that can depend on the problem
and the in the situation okay
that's pretty interesting so that's
again the the thing that actually the
infrastructure and the deployment might
have a big impact on what you're
actually doing as I said before the act
42 is completely independent of your
process so if in your process you have
to take infrastructure decisions first
and the template will definitely support
that and we have done some cross-cutting
concerns so what would that be
sometimes in your architecture work you
would probably decide sum or take some
decisions that will impact many many
components or building blocks or most of
the developers let's let's say you use a
no sequel database as an example
probably you want to store lots of data
and many developers have to comply to
your decision of using Cassandra or
whatever and we call those
decisions cross-cutting or conceptual
decisions like a principle the guiding
principle in this architecture to use
Cassandra database or it's a guiding
principle that we only use rest as the
interface technology whatever okay and
turn because we don't we don't ever want
to replicate or duplicate any
documentation we have taken those out or
factored out house and in this chapter
or part we call concepts or
cross-cutting concepts I see but that
would be general design decisions
concepts and yes we call those the
cross-cutting parts of the architecture
documentation architectural decisions
and these are that's quite interesting
these are other parts of the
documentation that are highly reusable
within an organization so for example a
bank or a logistics company that builds
several systems they will write quite
often be be able to reuse these these
concepts like the concepts how do we
monitor our application in production
you you decide that for a number of
systems and then you can reuse the
documentation and AK 42 is constructed
in a way that it makes reuse quite easy
so that's base create but there are
let's say add-ons that you could also
use one of them are quality scenarios
yeah people who know this architecture
trade-off analysis method they will know
the term quality scenario it's a way to
describe quality requirements in a very
exemplary way as a scenario how your
system shall fulfill us shall comply to
some quality requirements and in quality
scenario workshops with customers or our
clients we often come up with dozens or
even in the hundreds of such scenarios
which is valuable documentation but it's
it's a lot of stuff so we put that stuff
in more in the back corner of the
documentation as a reference and but we
don't want to make readers skim over
several pages and pages of quality
scenarios we quite often need them in
the long run but we put them in a in the
other section of the a k---forty -
because they are not not so heavily used
in day-to-day development so can you
give like a concrete example of such a
quality scenario my system shall respond
to a certain outage of the hardware in
the following way Oh an operator shall
be able to restart the database server
or the LDAP or whatever in a certain
time a special use case like generating
the monthly report shall be finished in
about a second and a half and so on and
so on
so that would be examples for quality
scenarios performance and reliability it
could be flexibility reliability
whatever and as I said I don't want to
repeat anything that's already described
in some requirements document but if I
learn about such a scenario during
development I need a place to fix it to
keep it and anywhere so I can reference
it probably later if I need it we had
this discussion about how quality six
are quite important and that this really
seems to be a way of starting to think
about quality and make it like really
concrete so do you think this is
important or not too important I'm a
little bit confused because you said
it's sort of an add-on and it's it's
something that you do in
in the back of the documentation let's
rewind our tape about 20 minutes and
when we talked about the beginning or
the first part of the architecture
template I said oh we need a very good
understanding a thorough understanding
of the problem and therefore there I
mentioned that quality belongs to the
problem part so the most important
quality attributes quality requirements
I want to know in the introduction to
some documentation but there will be
more information about required
qualities that probably have a little
lower priority or a bit more extensively
described and I want to put that out of
the reading flow out of the
understanding flow I see so this is
giving detail and it's not to say that
those details are not important it's
just that it might be a lot of detail
yes and it might be used as kind of
reference documentation and you you
don't want to read a reference manual I
I found that quite often we have about
five eight really important quality
scenarios I put this those in the at the
beginning of the documentation and the
85 others I put in the back okay I see
and what about the risks that's also
something like I can add on yes that's
an add on I really refuse to use in
reality because I think that risk
management is a management task so it
should be done by project owners or
project managers but if they don't do it
or if they don't do it properly and the
architects can come into play and help
them with risk management and we made
this and kind of add on chapter in act
42 because we found systems that didn't
manage their risks properly so we wanted
to give this room in the architectural
documentation especially ideas how we
can work against those risks actually I
have to admit I did very rarely use this
part of this documentation so I mean
obviously there might be a technical
risk like it might be hard to fulfill
the requirements for scaling or what
have you so is that something that the
ice tech would do and or is something
that the project manager would do or the
the architect should in my mind identify
these technical risks probably I can
myself as an architect do something
against those and but there are other
cases where I cannot do with with my
tooling with my means anything against
that risk so I need to probably escalate
that you said that you would hardly use
this part of the documentation at all so
you would just not care about the risk
and not even documented I would try to
convince my project manager to care
about risks and what them him or her let
them collect these risk manage those
risks if they don't do it and I would
come out to play in and so that would be
kept somewhere separate like in in the I
don't know a project documentation or
somewhere hopefully yes and you don't
want to do it redundantly that's why you
okay that's why you don't do it here
okay I see people people I know are in
companies I know have used this part of
the architecture documentation to
document their known technical depth Oh
therefore this this title risks is a bit
misleading but if you if you consider
this to be the known depth or the known
problems we have and that that becomes
much more interesting or important to me
that would be something we probably
incorporate into act 42 and one of the
next releases but I've seen that in
practice and I like that a lot
to make explicit things I I know some
there others bad code and hidden deep
into some layer but I need a place to
document that and it's it's silly risk
but it's not a risk that a project
manager can care about okay yeah makes a
lot of sense one of the questions is I
mean with with the documentation their
software is the problem that there are
quite a few different views and you know
information might be scattered
throughout the documentation so how do
you keep that consistent my answer to
this this question that comes up in many
many projects I've seen is make somebody
responsible for documentation I don't
mean make somebody write a lot of
documentation but make somebody
responsible for the right amount of
documentation and start small get
feedback from your stakeholders and if
the stakeholders readers whatever
whoever is interested gives you feedback
you can comply to that feedback you can
even
give more details or give less details
and so you come up with an appropriate
level of documentation and have somebody
responsible for this appropriateness
this guy's not paid for writing up pages
but he's paid for making customer
satisfied or readers satisfied such a
person will be really interested in
keeping things consistent one other
question is so why would I have a
security for example it's a typical of
those cross-cutting topics okay hope
that there is a chapter in the in the a
k---forty - template for this
cross-cutting stuff in a subchapter it's
labeled security so if you have security
as an issue that that would be the place
you would cover that I wouldn't put it
in as as a quality requirement yes the
the requirement is obviously a
requirement so security as a quality or
sub aspect of security you would really
need but the solution to this to this
requirement though what kind of
encryption you want what kind of hashing
do you want hardware encryption or
whatever that would be the solution to
the problem and the solution aspects you
would put in this cross-cutting stuff
next question so we've seen a lot of
templates and you know things that you
can document software development and
architecture is a creative process some
claim it's really an art what do you
think do you really need all of this
isn't it like just bureaucracy and just
standing in the way people who know me a
bit better know that I'm against
bureaucracy but I like documentation and
I think this can fit together with the
agile approach of having just the right
amount of documentation and several
definitions of done I've found in a
scrum context there is that saying we
accept only documented features so many
teams accept the fact that they need
some kind of documentation and we have
to find the right amount yes it there is
a risk that you write documentation in a
very bureaucratic way but you have a
very good chance to make that really
agile and to really adapt your
documentation to your stakeholders needs
and even for creative processes like
software you need some
some information apart from the source
code there are several kinds of
decisions you don't want a document in
the source code the reasons why you
choose a specific framework there is no
part of the source code suitable for
this kind of information so few things
need to be kept outside the code and
what kind of things I don't know what
the template gives you a structure for
it so you can write it easily and can
retrieve it easily okay so in a way what
you seem to be saying is that you
shouldn't fill out all of the templates
is that what you're saying
definitely not so you definitely don't
want to fill this like you fill your
text form but you you use only the parts
that are required so you do it in any
arbitrary order you seem fit in your
project or in your development and you
really use only those parts that add
some value to your communication to your
documentation so if within your team you
discuss certain aspects you will
probably want wanna document those are
the reasons why you decided for a
specific thing and you do that in any
order and if there I am very happy if
there are a lot of blank spaces in the
documentation because that shows we have
done that intelligently and we have
consciously decided which parts is
important and which parts we can leave
away and how do you do these decisions I
mean obviously there is the problem that
at the end you might have end up with
documentation that doesn't read the
document what needs to be documented so
it's hard to say whether this is just
something that I don't really need a
document or whether it's something that
I do need to document in my opinion only
the stakeholders of the system can
answer this question what they really
need or want so I would propose that in
a development you you ask your
stakeholders about the quality of the
documentation and show them examples
show them a table a diagram whatever
ask them do you need more do you need
less do you need other representations
what can I do to fulfill your
communication needs your information
needs and you you can incrementally
build your documentation from the
feedback you get and you wouldn't say
that there is like any sort of BAM
that you always need to fill out I mean
I could imagine that for example the the
qualities that are required would be
something that I would always put into
the documentation because there are so
caught actually solving the problem yes
excellent I propose to always have those
quality goals okay and the bare minimum
for me consists of the quality goals the
systems context with the external
interfaces and the high-level building
blocks building block structure so the
high level code structure I really want
to know because I don't want to read a
million lines of code to understand
what's going on I want to see this as an
as a white box overall picture and and
together with the qualities and the
context that would be the really bare
minimum I'd accept the buildings blocks
I could reverse engineer them from the
code Kuhn die I mean using these tools
yes probably if you know where to look
but imagine a system that's partly built
in Scala partly built in Java and has a
lot of si P functions and we rely on so
you you wouldn't probably know what
types of things to reverse engineer and
if it's just a small java application
then this is a trivial problem and that
is also I guess what it's what you would
start with right I mean the the context
the quantity goals and the building
blocks yeah I'm one of those overview
guys I I need an overview to understand
a problem so the biggest overview you
can give me is a context I'll describe
your external interfaces describe and
how this system as a black box fits into
its environment and then I'm quite happy
with the context so I would propose to
do this or start this at day zero so
when we start developing I want to know
the context where we start development
within what kind of data and events and
day one we can start thinking of maybe
infrastructure or how to implement some
use cases or do some bottom-up
prototyping definitely the context and
the quality goals would be something I
would do early in a development cycle
and how do you know where to stop I mean
how do you know that what you've written
is ready enough and there is nothing to
add we have defined the berm
so the questions were when do you stop
basically as I said before when my
stakeholder participants in the project
developers managers operators admins
whoever is participating when those
people tell me yes that's what you
showed me seems to be enough and and I
want to try to minimize that so I am I
was ask teams to be as minimalistic as
possible but don't take unnecessary risk
so I'd really like to ask people about
the quality of the documentation and I
and I like to repeat the questions over
and over again so I give them examples
of the documents every now and then to
get feedback if it's if it's ok ok
excellent and it would be the the same
document that you would show to all
these stakeholders I can imagine that
our operations people have quite a
different view on the system from
managers for example yeah good point in
an ideal world I would give him give
them projections I probably compile from
some kind of repository like a wiki or
an ASCII doc representation where really
compiled parts of the of the
documentation very specific for
operations for front-end developers or
back-end developers ok the the template
itself can be handled or can be
processed in a lot of different
representations or tools and in the
ideal world it's modular and you can
generate representations from it like
PDF for development and a PDF for
operation ok I see it's the template
enough or what I need to add anything
how do I get the most value out of it I
have seen enterprises that edit for
example like user interface
specifications like screen forms or UI
layouts to it and there is no common
common room for this kind of information
so organizations edit that I have seen
operation departments adding specific
things they need it like firewall rules
or things like like that which are not
part of the standard template but it's
it's a flexible template so you are
completely open to add things you really
need
and do that with care because it can
lead to some overhead but if you need
things and just add them which will show
you so it seems there is a lot of text
involved there there are some diagrams
would I just make it a Word document
that's a matter of taste or constraints
you have my personal favorite is user
wiki and use a modeling tool for
diagrams because I like modeling tools
they are very efficient in using
different kinds of static or dynamic or
deployment models but as I said you are
not stuck to two UML there so a wiki and
a modeling tool is a perfect combination
some some kind of textual syntax like
ASCII dog markdown textile whatever is
my second choice together with a drawing
tool I can include that into a build
process I can even test my documentation
or parts of my documentation and my
third priority is write it in a word
document okay but even if I'm
constrained to use just a word document
you can follow the template and you can
do it
agile and it it can really work so why
do you prefer a wiki over the other
approaches because I get collaboration
for free and I can send links to
specific parts of the documentation via
email
most wiki's have a stable URL scheme so
if I send you some link it's it will
still be valid a few months from now I
can reference my issue tracker in a wiki
and this is a very very nice integrative
tool suite it's full text search which I
don't get in a large number of what
documents and that makes collaboration
it seems quite easy okay and you said
the other alternative would be to put it
in your version control and to actually
test and compile the the documentation
so what does that mean I mean how do you
test documentation for example I can
check if links I use are valid and I can
include parts of source code I really
think important like interface
definitions whatever and that that kind
of basic semantic tests I can do and
the version control of a plain text
documentation has the advantage that
it's quite easy to generate different
representations from it and I know
clients that write their documentation
in ASCII tokomak down formats and
generate their confluence wiki from from
that now this is even yeah it's it's a
tooling problem or a tooling thing but
the template doesn't propose anything in
that aspect so how do you version the
documentation I'm if the documentation
is just in your versioning system that's
well obviously easy to do but what if I
have it in the wiki how do I make sure
that I have the same version for the
documentation and also the executable
system might be difficult for continuous
deployment but for many of my customers
use kind of release process even if it's
daily weekly or whatever for major
releases export the documentation as PDF
put them in the version control with the
same tag or label as your source code
and then you're fit okay and what you
automate that process or just do it
manually that depends on size of them
and system and I said before if there is
a person responsible for the
documentation these persons can decide
whether it's it's a nuisance to generate
the documentation then that automated if
you do it just once a month or once
every several months if you don't have
that many architectural changes then I
can live with a manual process do you
need to do any kind of divs again I mean
if you have a versioning system then
it's obvious that how it to do that but
what about diagrams and these kinds of
things in theory you can differ diagram
in practice I've never seen it working
yeah okay probably shouldn't tell us I
tell this to our listeners but print the
two documents and compare them visually
that's a bit faster it's it's it's not
nice but that works and usually you have
reasons why you change a diagram or why
you change and a big thing in the
architecture and you should care more
for the reasons behind the change and
then for the font size of a any
description
in your diagram so here is another
question that basically I texture is all
about you know certain decisions and
often at one point that this occurred to
me you wonder why that decision has been
made and then you look at the
documentation and you you realize that
it hasn't been properly documented so
how do I avoid that kind of situation
that you know you just made a decision
it's clear to everybody it's very
impolite oh well we didn't document it I
have no idea if you dive into the
template you will find several places
where we propose to document reasons and
before documenting facts because you
find the fact in the source code but you
don't find the reason in the source code
for example we have a thing called white
box template and the white box describes
the inner working the inner structure of
a thing and the most important for me is
describing the reason why the white box
looks like it looks so I'm if I see a
diagram I would like to know why the
diagram looks like this so why do I have
four components here and not five or
seven or whatever so we we point out
this reasoning about things the
arguments for four decisions at some
places in this template to make really
clear the importance of this kind of
information okay but there still I mean
if I make the decision and it might not
even be obvious that this is such an
important decision it's it only becomes
very important in hindsight how do I
avoid that situation that this kind of
information just gets lost yes you are
you are right the information can get
lost and probably you decide something
today don't document it and later on you
find out all this would have been an
important that template doesn't help you
in that case so it's just human error
basically yes but the template equity to
tries to remind you wherever possible
please explain the reason why you did
something but the template cannot
guarantee that you really do that one
more less obvious question is how do I
actually get started so if they're
convinced me to try it out what would
the next step be and how would I do
I have successfully started using the
template and several enterprises and we
we usually started by looking at some
examples and developers were sometimes
quite astonished Oh and that small
documentation service shall be
sufficient and they really like the idea
that they can do it in on small scale
that they can start small start very
agile and build it up so I propose you
have a look at some of the examples we
have we don't have that many different
examples that's for example one very
cool chess engine described in our 42
template we have some open source
projects described with AK 42i one or
two huge commercial systems described in
art 42 terminology or structure and have
a look at those and that will help you
get started and then take it from there
okay
are you aware by the way of any English
book about arc 42 that talks about that
currently I'm not aware of of English
publications and for the topic I get
some requests from British and American
companies and the template itself is
obviously available in several languages
but many of the examples are not
translated and I'm afraid so what other
languages except for German and and
English other Spanish and I know it's
used in France but we don't have an
official download for that most people
use the English version how are you
going to improve our 42 in the future is
there anything that is still on your
feature list or that you want to do yeah
we we moved a whole stuff to to github
about a year ago a bit more than a year
we are looking for several more tools
with support so other languages like
markdown textile whatever might be on
the roadmap generating Word documents
from asciidoc is on the roadmap but the
structure of the template itself is
relatively stable over time or has
stabilized a lot over time that's an
issue tracker so if anybody finds an
issue we'll do our best to fix it in
near real-time but on this tooling part
there's still open things to do
anything else you want to add anything
that we didn't cover any other stuff it
was a broad spectrum of things we
covered so I suggest listeners to just
give it a try have a look at and well
probably one of these small open source
projects and this and it's documentation
and if you like what you see it probably
is who will be working in your system so
just head over to aqua d to rhetoric and
start ok
thanks a lot oz potential talking to you
and thanks David yeah I hope you enjoyed
the show and have found with our coach
too so thanks for more information about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website @ SC - radio net to
provide feedback you can write comments
on each episode on the website or write
a review on itunes mention a message us
on Twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us a team at SES radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]